<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/overview.xsl"?>
<lesson>
	<id>14</id>
	<title>I wanted to learn English.</title>
	<summary>
		<content lang="ja_JP">Expressing intentions and desires</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">Expressing intentions and desires</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">Expressing intentions and desires</content>
	</summary>
	<description>
		<content lang="ja_JP">In this lesson, you will practise how to express intentions and desires. We will consider a new verb form, the "たい" form, which is used to express whether or not a speaker intends to perform an action. This form can be used in both statements and questions, but we will also examine how to use its positive and negative forms, as well as its past and non-past forms. We will also see how this form changes depending on whether the sentence is polite or plain. The forms you will be expected to know to complete this lesson are summarised below.</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">In this lesson, you will practise how to express intentions and desires. We will consider a new verb form, the "たい" form, which is used to express whether or not a speaker intends to perform an action. This form can be used in both statements and questions, but we will also examine how to use its positive and negative forms, as well as its past and non-past forms. We will also see how this form changes depending on whether the sentence is polite or plain. The forms you will be expected to know to complete this lesson are summarised below.</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">In this lesson, you will practise how to express intentions and desires. We will consider a new verb form, the "tai" form, which is used to express whether or not a speaker intends to perform an action. This form can be used in both statements and questions, but we will also examine how to use its positive and negative forms, as well as its past and non-past forms. We will also see how this form changes depending on whether the sentence is polite or plain. The forms you will be expected to know to complete this lesson are summarised below.</content>
	</description>
	<example>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Want To Do</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">私は日本語を習いたい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">わたしはにほんごをならいたい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">watashi wa nihongo o naraitai</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I want to learn Japanese.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">私は太郎と図書館へ行きたい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">わたしはたろうととしょかんへいきたい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">watashi wa tarou to toshokan e ikitai</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I want to go to the library with Taro.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Plan To Do</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">私は父と台所で朝ご飯を作るつもりです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">わたしはちちとだいどころであさごはんをつくるつもりです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">watashi wa chichi to daidokoro de asagohan wo tsukuru tsumoridesu</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I'm planning to make breakfast with my father in the kitchen.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">弟は庭に木を植えるつもりだった。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">おとうとはにわにきをうえるつもりだった。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">otouto wa niwa ni ki wo ueru tsumori datta.</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">My younger brother was planning to plant a tree in the garden.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Want</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">私は冷たいコーラが欲しい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">わたしはつめたいコーラがほしい。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">watashi wa tsumetai ko-ra ga hoshii</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I want some cold cola.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Want Someone To Do</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">私は妹に鉛筆を買ってほしいです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">わたしはいもうとにえんぴつをかってほしいです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">watashi wa imouto ni enpitsu o katte hosiidesu</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I want my younger sister to buy some pencils.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">兄にラジオを貸して欲しかったです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">あににラジオをかしてほしかったです。</content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">ani ni rajio o kashite hosikattadesu</content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I wanted you to lend my older brother your radio.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
	</example>
	<grammar_points>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 1: Desires to perform actions</b></u></font></p>
<p><font size="4"><b>1.1 The "tai" form</b></font></p>
<p>Sentences expressing the speaker's strong intention or desire to do something use a form of the verb called the "tai" form. This is a direct expression that corresponds to the English phrase "I want to ...", and puts the emphasis on the speaker's desire. Thus, it is stronger than the volitional form. To create the "tai" form of a verb, simply add "tai" to the stem form. Note that this form is only used for expressing the speaker's feeling or directly questioning the listener, and cannot be used to talk about the desires of a third party. In later lessons, we will cover expressions that can be used for this purpose.</p>
<p>The chart below reviews the stem form for each group of verbs, and shows how the "tai" form is constructed.</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Group</td><td>English</td><td>Dictionary Form</td><td>Stem form</td><td>"tai" form</td></tr><tr><td width="30">1</td><td>To go</td><td>行く</td><td>行き</td><td>行きたい</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>To drink</td><td>飲む</td><td>飲み</td><td>飲みたい</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>To play</td><td>遊ぶ</td><td>遊び</td><td>遊びたい</td></tr><tr><td width="30">2</td><td>To sleep</td><td>寝る</td><td>寝</td><td>寝たい</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>To eat</td><td>食べる</td><td>食べ</td><td>食べたい</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>To watch</td><td>見る</td><td>見</td><td>見たい</td></tr><tr><td width="30">3</td><td>To come</td><td>来る</td><td>来</td><td>来たい</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>To do</td><td>する</td><td>し</td><td>したい</td></tr>
</table>
<p>Next, we will examine the variations of the "tai" form using the same base sentence.</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Positive</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたい - "I want to go to Japan." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたいです - "I want to go to Japan." (polite)</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Positive, Past</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたかった - "I wanted to go to Japan." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたかったです - "I wanted to go to Japan." (polite)</td></tr>
</table>
<p>The negative case is shown below. Note that the polite form of the negative case differs slightly. We will cover the rules used to form the polite negative form in the next grammar point.</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたくない - "I don't want to go to Japan." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたくありません - "I don't want to go to Japan." (polite)</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Negative, Past</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたくなかった - "I didn't want to go to Japan." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>私は日本に行きたくありませんでした - "I didn't want to go to Japan." (polite)</td></tr>
</table>
<p><font size="4"><b>1.2: Conjugating adjectives and the "tai" form of verbs</b></font></p>
<p>Verbs in the "tai" form are conjugated in the same way as "i" adjectives. Thus, the various forms (positive and negative, non-past and past, polite and plain) are the same. Here are the rules for making the various forms from the non-past plain form of a verb in the "tai" form.</p>
<p>Negative: The negative form is constructed by dropping the final "i", replacing it with "ku", and then adding "nai".</p>
<p>Past: The past form is constructed by dropping the final "i" sound and replacing it with "katta".</p>
<p>Negative Past: First construct the negative form, and then apply the rule for making the past form. In other words, the final "i" is dropped and replaced with "ku nakatta".</p>
<p>Polite: If the sentence is positive, simply adding "desu" to the sentence changes it to the polite form. For negative sentences, the rules are a bit more complex because the portion after the "ku" sound actually behaves like the negative form of the existence verb "aru". So, for the non-past case "nai" becomes "arimasen", and for the past case "nakatta" becomes "arimasen deshita".</p>
<p>Here are a few examples that show the similarity between "i" adjectives and verbs in the "tai" form.</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Plain</td></tr><tr><td>今日は暑い - "It's hot today."</td></tr><tr><td>手紙を書きたい - "I want to write a letter."</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Plain, Negative</td></tr><tr><td>あのパンはおいしくない - "That bread isn't tasty."</td></tr><tr><td>パンを食べたくない - "I don't want to eat bread."</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Plain, Past</td></tr><tr><td>昨日はとても寒かった - "It was very cold yesterday."</td></tr><tr><td>英語を習いたかった - "I wanted to learn English."</td></tr>
</table>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 2: Intention to perform an action</b></u></font></p>
<p>This grammar pattern is used to indicate someone's intention to perform an action or plan to do something. Thus, it can only be used for verbs that describe a deliberate action. It can be used to describe the intentions of the speaker or third parties. It corresponds to the expressions "I'm planning to..." or "I intend to..." in English. While the "tai" form in the first grammar point can be used to talk about immediate desires or simple wants, "tsumori" implies that the subject has thought about the action for a longer time or has a stronger desire to perform it.</p>
<p>To form this grammar pattern, take a simple sentence with a verb in the dictionary form, and then add "tsumori" plus the copula (だ or です). The form of the copula used determines whether the sentence is polite or plain.</p>
<p>Note that when this grammar pattern is used in a question, it carries a strong implication of criticism. </p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr><td>来年ヨーロッパを旅行するつもりです - "I'm planning to visit Europe next year." (polite)</td></tr><tr><td>明日東京に行くつもりだ - "I'm planning to go to Tokyo tomorrow." (plain)</td></tr>
</table>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 3: Expressing desire with "hoshii"</b></u></font></p>
<p><font size="4"><b>3.1 Desire for objects</b></font></p>
<p>To express desire for an object, a special "i" adjective is used. While this word is classified as an adjective, the sentences that use it are closest to expression "I want ..." in English because they strongly emphasise the speaker's desire. See the examples below.</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Non-Past</td></tr><tr><td>リンゴが欲しい - "I want an apple." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>リンゴが欲しいです - "I want an apple." (polite)</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Past</td></tr><tr><td>コーヒーが欲しかった - "I wanted coffee." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>コーヒーが欲しかったです - "I wanted coffee." (polite)</td></tr>
</table>
<p>Note that "hoshii" can only be used to express the speaker's desires or in direct questions to the listener, so the forms practised in this lesson cannot be used when talking about a third party. Remember that the "tai" form of verbs also has this restriction.</p>
<p><font size="4"><b>3.2 Desire for others to perform actions</b></font></p>
<p>In addition to the usage described in the last section, "hoshii" can also be used to express desire or hope for another person to do something. While the "tai" form of a verb is used when the speaker wants to perform an action himself, this grammar pattern is used when the speaker wants someone else to perform an action.</p>
<p>In sentences using this grammar pattern, the person who the speaker wants to perform the action is marked by the direction marker に , followed by a simple sentence (optionally containing a direct object marked by the object marker を) with a verb in the "te" form that describes the action, immediately followed by "hoshii".</p>
<table align="center" width="90%" border="1">
<tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Non-Past</td></tr><tr><td>私は弟に野球をして欲しい - "I want my younger brother to play baseball." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>兄にラジオを貸して欲しいです - "I wanted you to lend my older brother your radio." (polite)</td></tr><tr bgcolor="#aaaaff"><td>Past</td></tr><tr><td>一緒に東京に来て欲しかった - "I wanted you to come to Tokyo with me." (plain)</td></tr><tr><td>友達にパーティーに来て欲しかったです - "I wanted my friend to come to the party." (polite)</td></tr>
</table>
<p>As in the second and third examples above, this pattern can be used to indicate that the speaker wants the listener to do something. However, be aware that this type of request is not polite and can sound forceful. Because of this, it is most appropriate when speaking to those of lower social standing, close friends, or family members. For polite requests, especially to people of equal or higher social standing, the grammar patterns covered in the earlier lessons should be used.</p>

	</grammar_points>
</lesson>
