<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/overview.xsl"?>
<lesson>
	<id>19</id>
	<title>I will try this.</title>
	<summary>
		<content lang="ja_JP">Intentional actions</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">Intentional actions</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">Intentional actions</content>
	</summary>
	<description>
		<content lang="ja_JP">This lesson will introduce various verbs which modify a sentence to indicate why an action was performed or the speaker's feelings on the outcome. First, it introduces a form which is used to show the speaker's desire to perform an action at some point in the future. Next, we will practise an expression used to show that an action is done in preparation for a future event. Finally, an expression that shows regret over an unintentional outcome is introduced.</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">This lesson will introduce various verbs which modify a sentence to indicate why an action was performed or the speaker's feelings on the outcome. First, it introduces a form which is used to show the speaker's desire to perform an action at some point in the future. Next, we will practise an expression used to show that an action is done in preparation for a future event. Finally, an expression that shows regret over an unintentional outcome is introduced.</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">This lesson will introduce various verbs which modify a sentence to indicate why an action was performed or the speaker's feelings on the outcome. First, it introduces a form which is used to show the speaker's desire to perform an action at some point in the future. Next, we will practise an expression used to show that an action is done in preparation for a future event. Finally, an expression that shows regret over an unintentional outcome is introduced.</content>
	</description>
	<example>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Desire to try</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">東京に一度<b>行ってみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">とうきょうにいちど<b>いってみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">tokyo ni ichido <b>itte mitai</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I'd like to try going to Tokyo once.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">あそこで<b>泳いでみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">あそこで<b>およいでみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">asoko de <b>oyoide mitai</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I'd like to try swimming there.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">彼とゲームの話を<b>してみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">かれとゲームのはなしを<b>してみたい</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">kare to ge-mu no hanashi wo <b>shite mitai</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I'd like to try talking to him about games.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Preparation</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">ビールを<b>買っておく</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">ビールを<b>かっておく</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">bi-ru wo <b>katte oku</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I will buy some beer for later.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">あらかじめ薬を<b>飲んでおく</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">あらかじめくすりを<b>のんでおく</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">arakajime kusuri wo <b>nonde oku</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I will drink some medicine beforehand.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Completion / Regret</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">待ち合わせに<b>遅れてしまった</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">まちあわせに<b>おくれてしまった</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">machiawase ni <b>okurete shimatta</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I was late for our meeting.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">ビールをもう<b>飲んでしまった</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">ビールをもう<b>のんでしまった</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">bi-ru wo mou <b>nonde shimatta</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I already drank all the beer.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
	</example>
	<grammar_points>

<p>All of the grammar points that we will learn in this lesson are verbs which can modify sentences. Much like auxiliary verbs, they are added to the "te" form of the verb in the sentence. The tense of the modifier verb determines the tense of the sentence.</p>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 1: Trying something out</b></u></font></p>
<p>When the "te" form of a verb is followed by the verb みる , the sentence has the meaning of trying something out. This pattern is used when the speaker is curious about the results or hasn't performed the action before.</p>
<p>In this lesson, we will use the "tai" form of みる to express that the speaker desires to try something out. The nuance of these sentences is that the speaker is interested in doing something that he hasn't done before. Sentences like this are often used when talking about things that cannot be done immediately, or when the speaker doesn't know when he will get the chance to do so.</p>
<p>日本に行ったらお寿司を食べてみたいです - "I'd like to try eating sushi when I go to Japan."</p>
<p>いつか中国へ行ってみたい - "I want to go to China someday." (plain)</p>
<p>The first example above could also be translated as, "I'd like to see what it would be like to eat sushi." In contrast, when expressing an immediate want the "tai" form of the verb is used instead of the "te" form plus みる .</p>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 2: Preparation</b></u></font></p>
<p>When the "te" form of a verb is followed by the verb おく , it shows that the action of the sentence is done for future convenience or in preparation for something. It is used when the subject intentionally plans in advance for some event.</p>
<p>出かける前に昼ご飯を食べておきましょう - "Let's eat before we go out."</p>
<p>今週テストがあるから、今日は勉強しておく - "Because there is a test this week, I'm going to study today." (plain)</p>
<p>今ジュースが安いですから、たくさん買っておきます - "Juice is cheap now, so I will buy a lot."</p>
<p>In the first example above, the implication is that the speaker would like to eat now so it doesn't have to be done later. The second example shows that the speaker is preparing for the test by studying in advance. In the third example, the speaker is buying juice to drink in the future.</p>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 3: Unintentional outcomes</b></u></font></p>
<p>When a sentence is modified by the verb しまう , it shows that the outcome of the event described was unintentional. This expression shows the speaker's regret or dissatisfaction with the outcome.</p>
<p>コップを壊してしまいました - "I accidentally broke a cup."</p>
<p>宿題を忘れてしまった - "I forgot my homework." (plain)</p>
<p>チョコレートを全部食べてしまいました - "I ate all of the chocolates."</p>
<p>In the third example, even though eating chocolate was an intentional action and thus under the speaker's control, the sentence shows his regret at eating them all. This implies that he only intended to eat some of the chocolates but ended up eating more than he planned.</p>
<p><font size="4"><b>Grammar Point 3.1 Completion</b></font></p>
<p>When しまう is added to the "te" form of a verb it can also show that an action was done thoroughly or that it was performed to completion. In this case, the result can be intentional. From a single sentence it can be difficult to determine which nuance (completion or an unintentional result) is intended, but this is usually clear from the context.</p>
<p>残りのご飯を食べてしまいました - "I ate all of the leftover food."</p>
<p>弟の服を洗ってしまった - "I finished washing my younger brother's clothes." (plain)</p>

	</grammar_points>
</lesson>
