<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/overview.xsl"?>
<lesson>
	<id>29</id>
	<title>The teacher has arrived.</title>
	<summary>
		<content lang="ja_JP">Introduction to the passive form</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">Introduction to the passive form</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">Introduction to the passive form</content>
	</summary>
	<description>
		<content lang="ja_JP">In this lesson we will study the passive and causative passive forms of verbs. The passive form is used to indicate that something was acted upon by someone else, while the causative is used to indicate that someone was made to perform an action by someone else. We will also study some special usages of the passive form, such as sentences that express sympathy for the passive subject or indicate respect towards someone of higher social status.

We will see examples of each of these kinds of expressions.
</content>
		<content lang="ja_KANA">In this lesson we will study the passive and causative passive forms of verbs. The passive form is used to indicate that something was acted upon by someone else, while the causative is used to indicate that someone was made to perform an action by someone else. We will also study some special usages of the passive form, such as sentences that express sympathy for the passive subject or indicate respect towards someone of higher social status.

We will see examples of each of these kinds of expressions.
</content>
		<content lang="ja_ROME">In this lesson we will study the passive and causative passive forms of verbs. The passive form is used to indicate that something was acted upon by someone else, while the causative is used to indicate that someone was made to perform an action by someone else. We will also study some special usages of the passive form, such as sentences that express sympathy for the passive subject or indicate respect towards someone of higher social status.

We will see examples of each of these kinds of expressions.
</content>
	</description>
	<example>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Causative Passive</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">東京に<b>行かされる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">とうきょうに<b>いかされる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">toukyou ni <b>ikasareru</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I will be made to go to Tokyo.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">バッグを<b>買わされる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">ばっぐを<b>かわされる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">baggu wo <b>kawasareru</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I will be forced to buy a bag.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">場所を<b>覚えさせられる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">ばしょを<b>おぼえさせられる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">basho wo <b>oboe saserareru</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">I will be forced to remember the location.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><content lang="en">Passive</content></title>
			<sentence>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">彼に<b>壊された</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">かれに<b>こわされた</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">kare ni<b>kowasareta</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">It was broken by him.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
				<item>
					<japanese>
						<content lang="ja_JP">強盗にバッグを<b>盗まれる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_KANA">ごうとうにばっぐを<b>ぬすまれる</b></content>
						<content lang="ja_ROME">goutou ni baggu wo <b>nusumareru</b></content>
					</japanese>
					<translated>
						<content lang="en">My bag was stolen by a mugger.</content>
					</translated>
				</item>
			</sentence>
		</section>
	</example>
	<grammar_points>

<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 1: The passive form</b></u></font></p>
<p><font size="4"><b>1.1 The passive form</b></font></p>
<p>In the sentences that we have studied up until now, the basic pattern has been that the subject is the actor who performs the action described by the verb. In the passive construction, the focus is shifted so that the subject is the person or thing acted upon. You can see the difference between these two types of sentences by comparing how they describe the same events.</p>
<table align="center" width="600" border="1">
<tr>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Active</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>猫が魚を食べました - "The cat ate the fish."</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>強盗が私の鞄を盗みました - "A mugger stole my bag."</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Passive</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>魚が猫に食べられました - "The fish was eaten by the cat."</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>私は強盗に鞄を盗まれました - "I had my bag stolen by a mugger."</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>In a passive sentence the subject marked with は or が is what is acted upon. The actor is marked with に and the passive form of the verb is used. If a direct object marked with を is present, it is acted upon by the actor, not the subject. To form the plain passive form of a verb, change the final "u" sound to "a" and add "reru" for group 1 and 2 verbs. The passive form of Group 3 verbs must be learnt. No matter what group the dictionary form is, changing a verb to the passive form always makes it a group 2 verb.</p>
<table align="center" width="600" border="1">
<tr>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Group</th>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Dictionary Form</th>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Passive Form</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>行く</td>
<td>行かれる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>飲む</td>
<td>飲まれる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>遊ぶ</td>
<td>遊ばれる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>寝る</td>
<td>寝られる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>食べる</td>
<td>食べられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>見る</td>
<td>見られる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>来る</td>
<td>来られる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>する</td>
<td>される</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>Compared to English, the passive construction is widely used in Japanese. Both the actor and the direct object may be omitted, either if they are understood from context or if the speaker doesn't want to go into detail. As in other sentences, the subject may be omitted as well.</p>
<p>この本は多くの人に読まれています - "This book is read by many people."</p>
<p>よく英語が上手と言われます - "I'm often told that my English is good." (subject and actor omitted)</p>
<p>この街は１００年前に作られた - "This city was built 100 years ago." (actor omitted)</p>
<p><font size="4"><b>1.2 Expressing respect with the passive form</b></font></p>
<p>The passive form of a verb can also be used to show respect when describing the actions of a person of higher social status. This type of sentence is somewhat politer than normal speech but not as polite as the honorific 'keego' forms that we will study later. Unlike other sentences with the passive form, in these type of sentences the subject remains the actor and only the verb is changed to the passive form. Thus, just like a regular sentence the subject marked with は or が is the actor and the direct object marked with を is acted upon by the subject.</p>
<p>鈴木先生は本を何冊も書かれました- "Professor Suzuki has written several books."</p>
<p>この問題についてどう思われますか - "What do you think about this problem?"</p>
<p><font size="4"><b>1.3 Expressing displeasure or sympathy</b></font></p>
<p>The passive form can also show empathy for a subject that suffers something or express frustration caused by an unpleasant event. In the latter case, the subject is often the speaker.</p>
<p>魚が猫に食べられました - "The fish was eaten by the cat."</p>
<p>私は雨に降られました - "I was rained on."</p>
<p>弟にテレビを壊された - "The TV was broken by my little brother."</p>
<p>A speaker might say the first example above if his pet fish was eaten, or if he felt sorry for the fish. In the second and third examples above, the subject is the speaker and these sentences express that he was inconvenienced by the outcome. Compare these with the sentences below, which merely state the facts in the active voice without using the passive to express sympathy.</p>
<p>猫が魚を食べました - "The cat ate the fish."</p>
<p>雨が降りました - "It rained."</p>
<p>弟がテレビを壊した - "My little brother broke a TV."</p>
<p>In terms of describing the events that happened, both sentences are identical to the original examples that use the passive form. However, the original passive examples express the speaker's unhappiness with the events, while these examples carry none of that nuance.</p>
<p><font size="4"><u><b>Grammar Point 2: The causative passive form</b></u></font></p>
<p>Recall that the causative construction that we studied in the last lesson is used to express that someone is allowed to or made to do an action. This construction can be combined with the use of the passive in section 1.3 to show that someone was forced to do something and did not enjoy it or that the speaker empathises with the subject who was forced to do something. Study the examples below.</p>
<p>田中さんは仕事をやめさせられた - "Tanaka was forced to quit his job."</p>
<p>私は母にピアノの練習をさせられました - "I was forced to practice the piano by my mother."</p>
<p>彼は友達にビールをたくさん飲ませられた - "He was forced to drink a lot of beer by his friend."</p>
<p>This pattern is formed by starting with a sentence in the causative form, and then applying the rules in grammar point 1.1 to change the sentence in to the passive form. Though this type of sentence may appear confusing at first, you can make sense of it if you take a look at the words that compose it. The subject, in other words the person who is made or forced to do the action, is marked with は or が . The actor, who forces the subject to do something, is marked with に . Direct objects, which are acted on by the subject, are marked by を . The verb shows the action that the subject was forced to do, and is in the causative passive form. Below is a table showing how the causative passive form is constructed for several verbs.</p>
<table align="center" width="600" border="1">
<tr>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Group</th>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Dictionary Form</th>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Causative Form</th>
<th bgcolor="#aaaaff">Causative Passive Form</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>行く</td>
<td>行かせる</td>
<td>行かせられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>飲む</td>
<td>飲ませる</td>
<td>飲ませられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>遊ぶ</td>
<td>遊ばせる</td>
<td>遊ばせられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>寝る</td>
<td>寝させる</td>
<td>寝させられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>食べる</td>
<td>食べさせる</td>
<td>食べさせられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>見る</td>
<td>見させる</td>
<td>見させられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>来る</td>
<td>来させる</td>
<td>来させられる</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>する</td>
<td>させる</td>
<td>させられる</td>
</tr>
</table>

	</grammar_points>
</lesson>
